Narrator: The Boy Who Harnessed the Wind
Part 1
William: …Standing on the porch one morning during a heavy rain,
I watched a line of people walking slowly past like a great army of ants.
They were our neighbours and farmers from other villages.
The women carried basins on their heads containing all their pots and pans,
water buckets, even bundles of clothing.
They stopped to rest every few metres, exhausted from hunger,
before hoisting their heavy loads and continuing on…
On the first day of February, the head teacher made this announcement at assembly.
‘We’re all aware of the problems across the country, which we also face,’ he said.
‘But many of you still haven’t paid your school fees for this term.
Starting tomorrow, the grace period is over.’
My hungry stomach tied itself into another knot because I knew my father hadn’t paid my fees
– 1,200 kwacha, collected three times a year.
When I got home, I found my father in the fields.
‘They’re saying I should bring my fees tomorrow, 1,200 kwacha,’ I said.
‘So we should pay them. They aren’t joking.’
My father gave me the look I’d grown to fear.
‘You know our problems here, son,’ he said. ‘We have nothing.’
I missed school terribly.
I remembered that the previous year a group called
the Malawi Teacher Training Activity had opened a small library…
that was stocked with books donated by the American government.
Perhaps reading could keep my brain from getting soft while being a dropout.
One day, I noticed a book pushed into the shelf and slightly concealed.
It was an American textbook called Using Energy.
The cover featured a long row of windmills
– though at the time I had no idea what a windmill was...
Presenter: William was fascinated by the giant machines that towered into the sky,
and when he discovered they could make electricity from the wind, he decided to try to build one.